Guide to the Robert McAlmon Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Robert McAlmon papers
1916-1980
1930-1952
YCAL MSS 293
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.71
(7 boxes)
The Robert McAlmon Papers consist of letters to McAlmon from literary friends, including William Carlos Williams, Ezra Pound, James Joyce, and Gertrude Stein; manuscripts of several of his writings; and a small quantity of photographs and related papers.
McAlmon, Robert, 1896-1956
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Robert McAlmon Papers are almost entirely the gift and bequest of Norman Holmes Pearson, 1969-1976, who purchased them from Robert McAlmon from 1949 on for eventual donation toYale.
Letters by Gertrude Stein, Ezra Pound, James Joyce, and William Carlos Williams were purchased by the Yale Collection of American Literature from Robert McAlmon beginning in 1949.
The manuscript of Paris, 14th of July is the gift of Richard Wayand, 1956.
The letters of Ernest Hemingway to Robert McAlmon are the gift of Donald Gallup in memory of Norman Holmes Pearson, 1976.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Existence and Location of Copies
Microfilm available through Access Services.
Robert McAlmon, 1895-1956
Robert McAlmon, American author, was born in Kansas, one of ten children of an itinerant minister, and raised in several Midwestern states. After a brief stay in Chicago, where he met Emanuel Carnevali, he moved to New York in 1920 and quickly joined the literary circle active in Greenwich Village. With his friend William Carlos Williams, he founded Contact magazine; its four issues published work by Ezra Pound, Wallace Stevens, Marianne Moore, Glenway Wescott, and H. D.
It was through H. D. that McAlmon met and married her lover, the shipping heiress Annie Winifred Ellerman, who published under the name "Bryher." Their 1921 marriage inspired much gossip concerning McAlmon's own sexual preferences and Bryher's financial support of him: some referred to him as "Robert McAlimony." In the following year, McAlmon moved to Paris and founded the influential Contact Editions press. Its publications included Hemingway's first book, Three Stories and Ten Poems (1923), poetry collections by William Carlos Williams, Mina Loy, and Marsden Hartley, and the first complete edition of Gertrude Stein's The Making of Americans (1925). He also provided James Joyce with financial support and assisted in the revision and typing of the Penelope section of Ulysses.
McAlmon's own published works from this period include the critically praised short story collections The Hasty Bunch (1922) and Distinguished Air (1925); the experimental "plotless novel" Village (1924); and a collection of poetry, Portrait of a Generation (1926). The McAlmons divorced in 1925, and McAlmon left Paris in 1929, after closing Contact Editions. Throughout the next fifteen years, he traveled widely in the United States, Mexico and Europe, drinking heavily and publishing little. Not Alone Lost, a volume of poetry, was published by New Directions in 1937 and became its worst-selling title. His bitter memoir of Paris in the Twenties, Being Geniuses Together, appeared in Great Britain to little notice in 1938.
McAlmon returned to the United States following the occupation of France in 1940. In ill-health and out of money, he settled in Arizona, where he worked as a salesman in his brothers' surgical supply company. His tuberculosis worsened in 1951, and his sisters bought him a small house in Hot Springs, California, where he died on February 2, 1956.
Scope and Contents
The Robert McAlmon Papers document portions of the life and work of Robert McAlmon and his decades-long connections with American and British members of the 1920s Paris expatriate community. The collection spans the years 1916-1956, but the bulk of the material is post-1930. The correspondence series includes substantive letters from many of the major literary figures of the period, including William Bird, Kay Boyle, T. S. Eliot, John Glassco, H. D., Hilaire Hiler, Ernest Hemingway, James Joyce, Katherine Anne Porter, Ezra Pound, Gertrude Stein, and William Carlos Williams, and from the musician George Antheil and the artist Marsden Hartley. The collection also contains typescripts of two of McAlmon's critically acclaimed publications, Distinguished Air and Village: Throughout Fifteen Years, and of several other works, including the never-completed Politics of Existence; and several folders of photographs.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Correspondence; II.Writings; III. Other Papers.
American fiction -- 20th Century; American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Authors, American -- France -- Paris; Expatriate authors -- France -- Paris; Small presses -- France; H. D. (Hilda Doolittle), 1886-1961; Antheil, George, 1900-1959; Barnes, Djuna, 1892-; Bird, William, 1888-1963; Boyle, Kay, 1902-1992; Eliot, T. S. (Thomas Stearns), 1888-1965; Glassco, John, 1909-1981; Hartley, Marsden, 1877-1943; Hemingway, Ernest, 1899-1961; Herbst, Josephine, 1892-1969; Joyce, James, 1882-1941; Lewis, Wyndham, 1882-1957; Macleod, Norman, 1906-1985; McAlmon, Robert, 1896-1956; Moore, Marianne, 1887-1972; Porter, Katherine Anne, 1890-1980; Pound, Ezra, 1885-1972; Satō, Ken; Stein, Gertrude, 1874-1946; Stern, James; Williams, William Carlos, 1883-1963; Contact Editions
- Correspondence, 1920-1959; Series I; 1.51; (3 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Series I, Correspondence, is alphabetically arranged by name of correspondent. One folder of general correspondence, also alphabetically arranged, is located at the beginning of the series.
  McAlmon's correspondence consists almost entirely of letters from literary colleagues and friends. There are no letters from other members of the McAlmon family and none from Bryher, his wife for several years. In fact, while his correspondents are almost all writers McAlmon met in New York and Paris in the 1920s, most of their letters date from after McAlmon left Paris in 1929.
  There are some 1920s letters from George Antheil, Djuna Barnes, T. S. Eliot, Ernest Hemingway, James Joyce, Wyndham Lewis, Marianne Moore, Ezra Pound, Ken Sato, and Gertrude Stein. These often discuss Contact Editions business, particularly Hemingway's and Stein's. Antheil's letters offer vivid discussions of his love of music and his personal "philosophy" about the relationship between art and sex, while Pound's are a mix of literary analysis, exhortations to read, circulate or publish various authors, and oblique comments on the social scene.
  Other major correspondents include William Bird, Kay Boyle, H. D., Marsden Hartley, Josephine Herbst, and James Stern. The letters of almost all the correspondents are a valuable source of information about the Paris expatriate circle and its "afterlife." Well into the 1950s, these writers and artists continued to follow each other's lives and careers, argue about the value of each other's works, and dispute each other's memories of Paris.
  Their often long letters are filled with personal news; gossip about about mutual acquaintances; and comments on each others' publications, sometimes highly negative. Those who returned to the United States often remarked on the high cost of living and the difficulties of readjusting to America after many years abroad. Marsden Hartley, back in Maine in August of 1941, complained that "I feel stuck here like a lobster trap washed up in the tide." Josephine Herbst wrote from Pennsylvania in June of 1949: "I can't tell you how I long to go back."
  Postwar letters from correspondents who had remained in or returned to Europe, including H. D. and William Bird, contain descriptions of the difficult conditions there and news of European friends. Ken Sato's letters detail postwar changes in Japan as well.
  Letters from the late 1940s and 1950s chronicle the writers' health and finances; the careers and marriages of their children; and their thoughts on current events in the United States. They also describe the authors' reactions to receiving questions about each other from biographers and historians and mention plans to donate or sell their literary papers. "Certainly sell Yale my letters, glad they can be turned into a little cash," advised William Carlos Williams in 1949.
  Relatively few correspondents in this series had no direct association with 1920s Paris. They include the Western poet Norman MacLeod and his wife Vivian; Joan Churchill; the Joyce biographer Richard Ellmann; and the Joyce collector John J. Slocum.
  - A-Z general, 1952-54, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Abbott, Berenice, 1952-53, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Antheil, George, 1920s (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Barnes, Djuna, 1920-52 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Beach, Sylvia, 1932-44 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bird, William, 1934-54 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes retained carbons of some letters from McAlmon to Bird
  - Boyle, Kay, 1934-53, undated (Box 1, Folder 8-10)
  - Charters, Jimmie, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Churchill, Joan, 1951-52 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Coates, Robert, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Coffey, Brian, 1939-53 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Cook, William, 1932-53 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Includes photograph of William Cook and friend, Paris, 1938
  - Dahlberg, Edward, 1953-54 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Dawson, Mitchell, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Einstein, William, 1942-52 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Eliot, T. S. (Thomas Stearns), 1921-26 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Ellmann, Richard, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Evans, Ernestine, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Gallup, Donald C., 1949-53 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Garrigue, Jean, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Includes typescript carbon of After the Three Bears
  - Glassco, John, 1941-47 (Box 1, Folder 24-26)
  - H. D., 1933-52, undated (Box 1, Folder 27-28)
  - Hall, Brian, 1939-52 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Hamnett, Nina, 1940-55, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Harbord, Gordon, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Hartley, Marsden, 1936-42, undated (Box 1, Folder 32-36)
  - Hemingway, Ernest, 1923-25, undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Herbst, Josephine, 1949-54, undated (Box 1, Folder 38-39)
  - Hiler, Hilaire, 1937-53, undated (Box 1, Folder 40-41)
  - Idlet, John Thomas, 1952-53 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Johns, Richard, 1952-54 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Joyce, James, 1921-34, undated (Box 1, Folder 44-46)
  - Lanham, Edwin, 1937, undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Larsson, Raymond Ellsworth, 1935-42 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    Includes manuscript copy of Elegy on Receiving the News of Mary Widney's Death
  - Lewis, Wyndham, 1922-27, undated (Box 1, Folder 49)
    General note
    Accompanied by typescript comment on letters by McAlmon
  - Lord, Martha, 1953-54 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - MacIntyre, Carlyle Ferren, 1937-53, undated (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Macleod, Norman, 1951-55 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Macleod, Vivienne Koch, 1946-49, undated (Box 2, Folder 53)
    Accompanied by annotated photocopies of letters
  - Mangan, Sherry, 1945, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Mannin, Ethel, 1936-51 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Marsh, Louise, 1931, undated (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Metcalf, Addison M., 1954 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Moore, Marianne, 1921-52 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Morgan, Louise, 1931-52 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Morrison, Louise H., 1929, undated (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Nordström, Ludvig Anselm, 1923-38 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Porter, Katherine Anne, 1932-59 (Box 2, Folder 62-63)
    Includes 1959 photograph of Porter and N. Tatsumokuchi
  - Pound, Ezra, circa 1925-59, undated (Box 2, Folder 64-66)
  - Prescott, Joseph, 1953-54 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Richardson, Dorothy, 1929-52, undated (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Sato, Ken, 1923-53, undated (Box 2, Folder 69-71)
    Includes typescript carbon of "Samurai Tales, Saikaki Ibata [XVIIe]" and three photographs of Sato and his house, undated
  - Sinclair, May, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Slocum, John J., 1947, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Spoerri, James F., 1950 October 25 (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Stein, Gertrude, 1925-1926 (Box 2, Folder 75-77)
    Includes signed copy of contract between McAlmon and Stein for Contact Editions publication of The Making of Americans
  - Stern, James, 1936-54 (Box 3, Folder 78-81)
  - Thirlwall, John Connop, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 82)
  - Ullman, Sara, undated (Box 3, Folder 83)
  - Vail, Laurence, undated (Box 3, Folder 84)
  - Varèse, Edward, 1952 June 17 (Box 3, Folder 85)
  - Werner, Morris, 1935, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 86)
  - Wetterau, Robert, 1948-52 (Box 3, Folder 87)
  - Widney, Willard, 1952, undated (Box 3, Folder 88)
    Includes typescript copy of Elegy on Receiving the News of Mary Widney's Death
  - White, Tiny?, 1946-47, undated (Box 3, Folder 89)
  - Williams, William Carlos, 1921-48 (Box 3, Folder 90-99)
    Includes multiple copies and photocopies, some annotated by Norman Holmes Pearson and Donald Gallup
  - Yale University Library, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 100)
- Writings, 1916-1952; Series II; 0.83; (2 boxes)
  Series II, Writings, is alphabetically arranged by title of work, with two folders of untitled clippings and short pieces located at the end of the series. All items are typescripts or typescripts carbon, mostly the latter. Contents include typescripts of McAlmon's most successful works, Distinguished Air and Village, as well as the typescript drafts of Politics of Existence. McAlmon described this unfinished work in a 1952 letter as "no autobiography, but a history of various encounters through many years."
  - Distinguished Air, typescript carbon, annotated, circa 1925 (Box 4, Folder 101)
  - The Nightinghouls of Paris, typescript carbon, corrected, 1929? (Box 4, Folder 102)
  - Paris, 14th of July, typescript carbon, corrected, undated (Box 4, Folder 103)
    Autograph title page inscribed to Charles Demuth
  - Politics of Existence, typescript carbon, 1952, undated (Box 4, Folder 104-111)
    Also known as History of Encounters
    Prefaced by a letter to Norman Holmes Pearson, 1952 December 8, describing this project
  - School for Unrest, 1st Novel of the Twenties, typescript carbon, undated (Box 4, Folder 112-114)
  - Some Take Their Moments, typescript and typescript carbon, corrected, undated (Box 5, Folder 115-125)
  - Too Quick for Life, typescripts carbon, two versions, undated (Box 5, Folder 126-127)
  - Village: Throughout Fifteen Years, typescript carbon, undated (Box 5, Folder 128)
  - Book reviews, drafts of brief articles, newspaper clippings, some annotated, 1916-35, undated (Box 5, Folder 129-130)
- Other Papers, 1969-1980; Series III; 0.63; (2 boxes)
  Series III, Other Papers, consists of six folders of photographs, a photocopy of a dissertation about McAlmon, and seven folders of transcripts, photocopies, and photonegative copies of letters in Series I.
  The photographs are nearly all 5x7 portraits of people in black-and-white; most of them were probably taken in the 1920s and 1930s. Individual subjects include Kay Boyle mountaineering in the Swiss Alps; McAlmon's wife Bryher; the bullfighter Quinito Caldentey; Ernest Hemingway; William Carlos Williams; and McAlmon himself. There are also several group portraits, apparently taken in Paris.
  - Photographs, undated (Box 6, Folder 131-136)
  - Smoller, Sanford, Robert McAlmon: A Biographical Evaluation, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 137-152)
    Typescript photocopy
  - Transcripts and photocopies, 1969-80, undated (Box 7, Folder 153-173)